{
  "reference_number": "10845",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "To the best of my knowledge net zero emission is not possible as there is no way on a large scale to mitigate emissions that come\n\n from permanently under the ground (coal oil gas and limestone). Forestry is only a temporary holder of carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "How many people filling in this form understand the difference between carbon emissions that come from a permanently locked up\n under the ground source and those that originate from the atmosphere to where it is returned. e.g. Methane that comes from oil or\n gas extraction is exactly the same gas as ruminants produce by eating grass, but one is adding to the atmospheric carbon and the\n\n other is adding zero."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We do not know what science will come up with so obviously we have to be flexible."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We have to stop adding NET carbon to the atmosphere where we can (Livestock do not add net carbon from methane - except for\n\n the coal oil and gas we use to produce meat and wool etc). At this stage in history we cannot permanently mitigate or off-set our coal\n oil and gas use on a large scale so the first achievable goal should be to produce all our electricity by renewable sources - which\n means more hydro dams. Many people believe we can mitigate our carbon emissions by planting trees where the reality is it just buys\n\n a little time and until people realise this they are unlikely to change their habits. Planting a tree will not permanently mitigate your air\n New Zealand flight emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Use science and evidence based information taking into account the economics off all actions. The issue is NET carbon and people\nneed to be informed they cannot, at this stage in history, permanently mitigate their coal oil gas and limestone use - which will help\n\npeople realise they have to change their habits and why Governments make the decisions they do."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As a farmer I would like to make a couple of points. 1. The wording of Agriculture not being in the emissions trading scheme is\nincorrect and misleading - plus it makes us look like we are being subsidised by the city majority. Agricultural emissions, I assume, are\n\nMethane produced by Ruminants and Nitrous oxide. Methane (CH4) produced by ruminants in a steady state (i.e. numbers not\nchanging) is increasing carbon in the atmosphere by ZERO (unlike Methane from the the oil and gas industry, which is a by-product,\n\nwhere all added carbon is cumulative in the atmosphere). I started farming in 1980 and if the stock numbers are the same now as\nthen - my livestock have added ZERO carbon or methane to the atmosphere so therefore ZERO CLIMATE CHANGE, but all my usage\nof coal oil limestone and gas, including methane has increased the concentration in the atmosphere therefore aiding man induced\n\nclimate change. How could it be justified to charge a farmer for livestock produced methane if that methane is in a steady state and\nnot adding any carbon to the atmosphere or adding to man induced climate change. Methane is a short lived gas of approx 9-12\n\nyears. I realise the planet would be better off if sheep, cattle and deer were not ruminants but us farmers are helping to pay for world\nleading research into minimising livestock methane emissions. I believe the non farming community do not understand that livestock\n\ndo not produce carbon - they recycle it. Generally farmers are doing their best to minimise Nitrous Oxide emissions. 2. As I have\nalready stated I believe many people do not realise that forestry just buys the planet a little time and will not permanently mitigate our\n\ncoal, oil, limestone and gas emissions. I say this as someone who has planted many thousands of Pinetrees from an early age till now."
    }
  ]
}
